Ravishankar Ramanathan, Seattle, WA 98115

650-804-4264

raramana@gmail.com

https://www.linkedin.com/in/ravishankarramanathan/

Web Applications Development and Middleware Operations

Experienced Manager using agile and phase-based methodologies to deliver software on time and on budget. Proven success at managing stakeholder expectations, developing solutions that lower operational costs and continuously improving processes and team efficiency. Key competencies include:

- · Cloud Services
- Program & Project Management
- Enterprise Architecture & Systems Integration
- Oracle RDBMS 11g & 12c

- · Application Design
- Agile & Waterfall Software Development
- Oracle Portal, WebLogic Software
- Oracle Identity, Access & Authentication Manager

- · Project & Issue Tracking
- Continuous Integration/ Continuous Delivery
- Collaboration & Code Management
- Git, Java, Jenkins. Jira, LDAP, Python, RunDeck, Splunk, SQL

EXPERIENCE

National Ignition Facility, Lawrence Livermore National Labs, Livermore, CA November 2011 – March 2017 Engineering Lead - Middleware, Security and IAM

Guided, shaped, and supported the corporate strategic vision and day-to-day operations as a member of NIF's core operations and development team in various roles

- Held Department of Energy top secret clearance (Q)
- · Led multiple software and infrastructure engineering projects
- · Remotely managed teams between 2014 and 2017

Middleware Standardization (2012 - 2017)

Formed team of 12 in NIF's matrixed environment to lead development of upgrading internal applications running on old hardware and software

- Managed 2 developer leads and 10 developers and supervised their day-to-day tasks in an agile environment
- Drove stakeholder buy-in for migration of applications running on obsolete platform to a cloud platform
- Evangelized value proposition, status, and strategic roadmap to CTO and management on migration project
- · Mentored developers and leads, established challenging goals and conducted performance evaluations
- · Standardized JVM, log and configuration files, application server and library versions, status reports, alerts
- · Conducted quality/ risk reviews across portfolio to identify and escalate impediments to timely delivery
- Setup reports to gain insights into user behavior, application usage and failures, and performance problems

Security Framework Re-architecture (2014 – 2017)

Investigated gaps in security framework, developed plans to address the shortcomings of existing architecture and scheduled delivery timeframes to usher in a revamped framework in Java

- Headed team of 2 team leads and 1 developer for security framework revamp using agile methodologies
- · Partnered with team leads, developers, testers and operations lead to develop user stories
- · Drove engineering practices to increase velocity and delivered incremental features in 2-week sprints
- Extended security framework to support Active Directory groups for role based access control
- Eliminated clear passwords from corporate network by implementing identity credentials encryption
- Successfully managed CTO level visibility project involving DOE audit of Security and middleware stacks

Identity & Access Management (2012 - 2014)

Implemented Identity & Access Management and Single Sign-On for 1,200+ users

- Led team of 2 and delivered SSO and unified IAM services in development and production environments
- · Proactively engaged development teams, operations and end users to increase adoption of single sign-on
- Defined requirements to support identity lifecycle events (onboard, rehire, transfer, update, terminate)
- Delivered custom identity management solution that synchronized downstream security repositories with AD
- Audited commercial software usage and streamlined software licensing to save \$135,000 annually

DevOps (2012 - 2014)

Launched various DevOps tools to build, test and deploy internal software automatically

- Deployed Jenkins with Active Directory support to manage CI/ CD for NIF's development and test teams
- Setup Git to enable versioning of configuration files and scripts for middleware operations
- · Automated application server domain creation and access manager resource management using Python
- Supported use of RunDeck to manage self-service access to middleware operations
- Deployed Apache JMeter within development and testing community to load test performance issues
- Distributed Oracle management agents to discover, monitor and manage resources

IT Operations (2011 – 2017)

Owner of web, application, single sign-on services running on internal private cloud

- Managed day-to-day activities of an operations lead and a development lead to deliver middleware services
- Implemented high availability middleware services on a private cloud for 100+ applications and 1200+ users
- Supported 24/7 operations at NIF by managing 200+ VMs, 2+ million hits daily from users and services
- Improved business performance by identifying bottlenecks in mission critical business processes
- · Created metrics driven reports and statuses from thousands of machine data sources using Splunk
- Shared poor performance, compliance risks, and lost efficiency findings with teams to realign their work

Self-Employed, Bronx, NY

August 2005 – February 2007

Consultant

Provided consulting services to small firms that lacked IT departments

Web application development (2005 - 2007)

Designed web applications and provided IT services

- Developed real estate lead generation website components for Reply! that interfaced with Trulia listing data
- Decommissioned NYBrokers online presence of small stock brokerage firm and met regulatory requirements

Oracle Corporation, Reston, VA

February 1998 – August 2005

Software Development Lead, Oracle Portal

Built a world-class enterprise product that supported a global customer base with full internationalization and localization.

Import Export Subsystem (2001 – 2005)

Managed the development of 4 major releases of migration component of Oracle Portal software that was used by Fortune 500 companies

- Built a team of 11 that included 5 developers, 3 testers, 2 document writers and 1 PM located around world
- Remotely managed on-shore and off-shore teams spread across UK, India and US between 2000 and 2005
- Developed requirements, design, implementation and release plans, and documentation for Import/ Export
- Held customer advisory board meetings with PM and clients to tailor requirements to meet their usage
- · Designed a patent winning framework that allowed both in-band and out-of-band migration of portal objects
- · Successfully introduced durable identifiers (GUID) in base system objects to improve overall robustness
- · Built a schema validation utility that identified data inconsistencies in the base system and spun off a new tool
- · Improved product quality by significantly reducing the defect backlog from hundreds to less than 20 defects

Content Management Subsystem (1999 – 2001)

Designed back-end & front-end features of Oracle Portal content management subsystem

- Developed new design-time navigation UI to aid discovery of content management objects
- · Developed content management design-time features including content creation, classification, translation
- · Mentored developers on the best practices in software development through code audits, code reviews

Workflows (1998 - 1999)

Built web front-end to manage document approvals, routing and versioning workflows

EDUCATION

M.S., Electrical & Computer Engineering, George Mason University, Fairfax, VA B.E., Instrumentation Engineering, Annamalai University, India

PATENT

"Approaches for migrating portal objects from a source installation to a target installation." US Patent No 7346627, filed February, 2004 and issued March, 2008